war got real complicated in 1945 it used
to be that we'd look collectively at the
bodies of the dead in our war our shared
sacrifice and well if we had have purged
exhausted the energy of the conflict and
the blood in this case almost
universally for quite some time over the
20th century at least did the young men
who died in the trenches around about
1945 we found ourselves in a very
uncomfortable situation where we've got
right up to the threshold and had this
thing looking back at it's called
mutually assured destruction we had to
start figuring out how to shift the
boundary conditions and how we exercise
that that impulse the impulse of
you the impulse would punch you in the
face or hit you at the rock I think
there's a finding that it's very
powerful like it's that that's an
embodiment of the Christ myth and it in
a in a sense right I think I've said
this on a previous conversation I think
with Jack Murphy which was 2,000 years
we had a story where we were invited to
live in a certain way for the past
hundred years we've had a story where we
actually have to figure out how to we've
got no choice and every day the how
would I call it the pit gets wider and
deeper and closer to our toes 1945 just
where else make in 1962 just Khrushchev
and Kennedy could have plunged the world
into nuclear abyss just two guys and all
they had to do is not push the button
but every day and every way we just get
better and better at killing everybody
which means we got to get better and
better at not killing everybody in that
that that age-old thirteen point five
billion year habit when push comes to
shove pushing and shoving we have to
actually figure out how to not do that
we have to actually learn how to anchor
ourselves in that space of peace to
consistently and always as individuals
and as a collective to make that choice
to freely associate
and it's right there it says I feel like
wewe sort of if we step back and sort of
look at it we can tell that we're
currently right now living in two worlds
simultaneously you can feel the energy
of the of the Gerard Ian's conflict
scarcity mentality that any moment wants
to just tear apart the whole story
pardon me on the other hand the other
side salvation but that's the question
that I was you know because the
ambiguous part that I was alluding to is
the idea that well yes scarcity tends to
be the occasion for the impulse to find
a scapegoat to resolve the tension if
there's a famine if there's a plague if
there's lack of resources if there's a
murder spree whatever it is something
creates scarcity scarcity of life
scarcity of food scarcity of existence
scarcity of order scarcity of resources
scarcity of health and that triggers
this hunt for the scapegoat so we're
still trying that today but my question
is that some people would suggest and
there's a quote I think it's
I think it's does they have ski or
someone that says basically that if we
would resolve all scarcity issues if we
can resolve all material want would
human being stop their conflict and it's
like no there's something about here it
means that you could meet all their
needs and they would still find ways to
create eternal drama so that's my
question is is it really in Iraq my mind
about this all the time because I'm
always on the hunt for things that could
provide solutions for scarcity and I
think about all right let's find energy
too cheap to meter that's abundant you
know what would that do to alleviate the
social pressures to attack everybody
based on collective identities and
Nations and bombings and all these
things with that with it would that
reduce it a little bit and then what if
we could have you know cures for cancer
and Alzheimer's and diabetes and all
these terrible things that are people
are stressed out about they have this
latent death anxiety and that bothers
them knowing that people they love
around them will have these afflictions
that don't really seem to have any
resolution or cure imagine we could just
cure all those different things in our
lifetime so we chew our pollution we
cure energy scarcely reach or diseases
that have been afflicting and scaring us
would we still have the same level of
conflict or would it reduce it that
there is Jabba the Hutt all right that
that's the thing we're the thing that's
actually the problem which is the fear
at your heart all right so to be the
basis of your choice is fundamentally
anchored in fear and you try to solve
that by endeavouring to extinguish
scarcity in the outside and you you
create
neucopia of muchness and you you've
actually not solved the problem even the
least bit you haven't stepped it in
practicum in ways you actually get more
fearful in in the core and there's
another way alright the other way is to
sort of recognize it the only zero to
one
the only real bit that slips the only
real change that could ever happen is at
that basis of choice how much are you
are you able to have the basis of choice
the thing that is at the bottom of how
it is you're coming into the choices or
you're making how much are you able to
achieve coming into that place from the
space of love or peace or grace but if
you're torn you'd like to use and
they're all all part of the same complex
they can't really be named or fear or
sin alright that's it because you know
and we have plenty of stories that
people who've been able to make that
shift if you can come from that place of
love and you perceive a possibility of
material scarcity real scarcity the way
you relate to that real scarcity is just
completely different
contrariwise if you come from a place of
fear and you're sitting in a world of
absolute plenitude you're still an
asshole you can't help greed will still
drive a lot of your choice making so the
question is how
can you ground yourself in that other
place and it doesn't mean for the least
bit you're going to get rid of the
aspect of reality that is bounded by
thermodynamics and that's still a
fundamental characteristic of reality
what it means is that your choice making
will not be dominated by that
characteristic of reality your choice
making will first and foremost be coming
from this other location and it will be
you know now we're back to the loaves &
Fishes
I thought as a parable your choice
making will always be saying let us
think more deeply let us consider more
fully how it is we may find a way to
achieve abundance in this space if we
can maintain the capacity to not be at
each other's throats now
thirteen point six billion years into
this game we've got a lot of instincts
that are oriented towards scarcity it'll
probably be another thirteen point six
billion years before we can be so fully
anchored in the other side of that
equation that we can feel like it's a
real forever all the time but there's
definitely a sort of a 50/50 how often
in your choice is coming from one place
to the other
how are where are you what's the basis
of your choice to what degree are you
unconsciously acting that is scarce into
what degree are you able to say oh
sorry about that I just made a choice
out of this place how well can you come
back into this new basis how well can
you recover when you get kind of knocked
off your path can you sail off the path
and before I do anything else cuz if I'm
off the path most of my choices are
probably gonna create harm before I do
anything how do I get back on the path
how do I what is it twelve steps how do
I came from where the third step is but
is somewhere in the direction of how do
i atone for my from the trespasses that
I've made against others while I've been
unconscious while I've been off the path
that's just skillfulness right it's not
that different some sense from learning
how to juggle not easy but you can do it
and once you've done it
it doesn't mean you're perfect it
doesn't mean like if you're juggling and
somebody comes and shoves you that
you're not going to drop the balls but
it does mean that you can do something
there's a skillfulness and the capacity
to orient yourself towards this basis of
choice anchored in grace and love become
more and more capable of staying in that
place and knowing when you're out of it
and always knowing how to come back to
it and then of course in that place
everyone who has that skillfulness has a
capacity to be in relationship with
everyone else who has a skillfulness
that is oriented towards generativity
and that is the basis of true plenitude
and this is I think this is the real
conflict the real competition there's a
competition between the instincts that
is are oriented toward scarcity which is
to say well first and foremost I want to
be the boss and I want to make everybody
else be micro nema something called the
rules for rulers oh go ahead what's the
rule is really good case study of the
logic of scarcity and how important how
how fearful a dictator must be of their
the
directly underneath them because of
course no human can ever rule a tribe of
people at the end of the day each of us
are just one person it's only people
allowing themselves to be ruled and they
allow themselves to be ruled in a series
of surrendering their sovereignty and so
if you're the boss you're the boss
because by virtue of the five to ten
people who directly are underneath you
and so people right underneath you who
are your enforcers and perhaps your your
your operators and your organizers each
one of them looks at each other as a
rival it's rivalry at the top more so
than anything else but if you're good at
what you do you can use the rules for
rulers and keep things hanging together
and maintain yourself and your cabal as
being at the top of the scarcity pyramid
and of course you want to make
absolutely certain that everybody at the
bottom of the scarcity pyramid is also
making a local game theoretic choice to
not pull together if anybody else at the
bottom of that pyramid lest you be
overthrown so that that's the game I
think the game on that on that side of
the equation the game based on the basis
of fear is that game how do I maintain
my cell phone my cabal at the top of the
scarcity pyramid and how do I manage
that pyramid pyramid by through hook or
by crook all right I can lie I can bribe
thinking about for how Saudi Arabia
manages its population and it's got a
small cabal of people who are
aristocrats on top and they got lots of
resources so they just make sure that
they main make the people fear violence
enough and appreciate seek violence
little enough that they stay well
managed herd
they stay in the cattle zone of humans
other than you and the pyramid maintains
right that's one structure and of course
it's a it's a structure that we've seen
for a long time that's the domain of the
sacred you just described the idea
that's the domain of the sacred that
that sacred violence staves off profane
violence right and so it's so that's the
second the second one is her sacred
violence staves off profane violence all
right the first one is fear of profane
violence maintains a tacit agreement to
stay in the profane and
big piece of the profane is to simulate
and also to parasitize the sacred
thinking about the movie Star Wars you
ready I'm gonna go straight 1970s kid
for you
well George Lucas did a terrible and
horrible and wonderful thing at the same
time he tapped into Joseph Campbell and
he crafted a parable tapping into our
mythopoetic sacred and the deep roots of
sacred which every child who watched
that movie was like oh okay that you
know my instincts that have been born
through a lot of countless generations
trying to sense what is right and what
is wrong and that story resonates with
it method when I look around me watching
Saturday morning cartoons and TV
commercials I don't see much of it so
even though it's a thin gruel of
mythopoetic sacredness it's more and
more than nothing and then he proceeded
with a good help of the folks at Disney
even more so to strip-mine the sacred as
maximally as possible to feed the job of
the HUD character in the profane and
make us lose sight of the difference
between the sacred and the profane but
there is a difference right on the other
side is the sacred violence the other
side is the the
not rules for rulers voluntary
association we've got two goddamn term
for it
people actually recognizing that to come
together entirely voluntarily out of
wisdom out of
a felt sense of the reality of community
that we are in fact all part of the
brotherhood of man it is inevitable and
has always been thus we are family in a
deep sense and I don't mean that
artificially I mean that really to
actually do it and you know going back
to homesteading you get ten strangers
and you have them build something
together and have them live or die by
the by the virtues of their own hands
and nine of them will actually become
family typically one of them will still
bind kind of an asshole not necessarily
you got to keep your eye out for that
one
because that's part of the story as well
all right so I think that we can
continue to tap on that that that
distinction between the sacred and the
profane the distinction between the
fear-based scarcity mentality not
scarcity itself with the mentality that
is using fear to maintain is if I'm one
of us is gonna starve it's going to be
you and the the state of grace of being
in the abundance mentality which says
well neither of us needs to starve if we
work together